Guide to the Mexico Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Chronological, 1522-1915; Part II. I
  - Title: Documents on Santa Ana's occupation of San Luis Potosí. Places: San Luis Potosí. Mexico City, Charcas, and Guadalcazar. Description: Copies of documents related to General Antonio López de Santa Ana's occupation of San Luis Potosí. Included are an act by provincial and city authorities concerning Santa Ana's pronouncements; a proclamation by General José Gabriel Armijo, the federal general sent to oppose Santa Ana; and a manifesto from the city council regarding Santa Ana's conduct during his occupation of San Luis Potosí. Also found are documents related to a plan [for a revolt?] by José Márquez, a colonel in the army commanded by General Armijo. A note at the end of the texts states all these copies were taken from El Sol de México. 1823 (Box 50, Folder 795, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Nombrado por V. M. Y. para la comisión...." Description: Incomplete text discussing the actions of Emperor Itúrbide. The text also discusses the Plan of Casa Mata. 1823 (Box 50, Folder 796, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Fundación del Archivo General de la Nación." Place: Mexico City. Description: Documents concerning the appointments of Juan de Dios Uribe and Ignacio Cubas to positions in the national archive. 1823 (Box 50, Folder 797, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Prontuario para la esacción de los 12 marvedises que se ecsigen en virtud de lo dispuesto en Real Orden...." Place: [Mexico City?]. Description: Two tables dealing with financial exactions from salaried employees. The first details contributions required by a royal order dated 1799. The second table (1817-1823) details exactions from the wages of four classes of employees based on orders of the Spanish Crown or Mexican national congress. ca. 1823 (Box 50, Folder 798, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Regimento Ynfantería 2° Provincial...." Description: Record of payments made by the national treasury to the second provincial infantry regiment. 1823-1824 (Box 50, Folder 799, Reel 12)
  - Title: Texts concerning government in San Luis Potosí. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Documents concerning a meeting of the provincial deputation about two dispatches from Querétaro's provincial deputation, and the appointment of the marquis of Jaral as the state's governor. 1823-1824 (Box 50, Folder 800, Reel 12)
  - Title: Documents by the marquis de Vivanco. Place: Mexico City. Description: Included are a communiqué to an unidentified person concerning military personnel matters, and a decree concerning a particular soldier's military pay. 1823-1824 (Box 50, Folder 801, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Informe de Don Ignacio de Cubas sobre el arreglo del Archivo general." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a report on the state of the national archive, written by its director. 1824 Jan 10 (Box 50, Folder 802, Reel 12)
  - Title: Diputación provincial del Nuevo León. Place: Monterrey. Description: Letter sent by Nuevo León's provincial deputation to Coahuila's provincial deputation concerning defensive measures, and the march of troops from Saltillo to the province of Santander. 1824 Jan 29 (Box 50, Folder 803, Reel 12)
  - Title: Communications from the Primera Secretaría de Estado to the jefe político of San Luis Potosí. Place: Mexico City. Description: Series of communications concerning a variety of subjects including the adherence of San Luis to the union; the patriotic conduct of the provincial deputation; a complaint filed by Vicente Romero; the re-election of ayuntamiento members; the pious fund of the Californias; and the receipt of the list of members of the state congress. 1824 Jan-Apr (Box 50, Folder 804, Reel 12)
  - Title: Decree. Places: Mexico City and San Luis Potosí. Description: Copy of a decree, originally issued on 1824 February 12, ordering the continuation of the tobacco monopoly. The decree lays out the monopoly's rules and regulations. 1824 Mar 6 (Box 50, Folder 805, Reel 12)
  - Title: Order to the customs house. Place: Mexico City. Description: Order from the treasury ministry to the customs house in Veracruz concerning procedures for determining customs duties on liquor and wine. 1824 Apr 10 (Box 50, Folder 806, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Comiciones del h. congreso y diputados que la componen." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Chart listing the members of the state congress's standing committees. 1824 Apr 28
    See: Oversize, folder 11
  - Title: "Gobernación del Estado Libre de San Luis Potosí." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Copies of three early decrees by the constituent congress of San Luis Potosí. The decrees deal with the organization of state government, the oath of allegiance to the assembly, and other matters. 1824 Jun 8 (Box 50, Folder 807, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter to the state congress of Coahuila. Place: Guanajuato. Description: Cover letter for three copies of a manifesto sent by the secretariat of Guanajuato's state congress. 1824 Jul 7 (Box 50, Folder 808, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter from the "Secretaría del Congreso de Querétaro." Place: Querétaro. Description: Letter of goodwill addressed to the state congress of Coahuila. 1824 Sep 3 (Box 50, Folder 809, Reel 12)
  - Title: Order from the Secretario. Place: Mexico City. Description: Order from the "Secretario de Estado y del despacho de relaciones" that fifty copies of any order from a federal ministry be printed at government expense to help an unidentified state. 1824 Sep 4 (Box 50, Folder 810, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter from the "Secretaría del Congreso del Estado Libre de Xalisco." Place: Guadalajara. Description: Letter of goodwill addressed to the state congress of Coahuila. 1824 Sep 9 (Box 50, Folder 811, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter from the "Secretaría del Congreso de Oaxaca." Place: Oaxaca. Description: Letter of goodwill addressed to the state congress of Coahuila. 1824 Sep 10 (Box 50, Folder 812, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter from the "Secretaría del Honorable Congreso del Estado de Chihuagua." Place: Chihuahua. Description: Letter of goodwill addressed to the state congress of Coahuila. 1824 Sep 21 (Box 50, Folder 813, Reel 12)
  - Title: Report to the Ministro de Estado y del Despacho de Relaciones. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Report from San Luis Potosí's state government dealing with internal government, public welfare, development (mining, agriculture, commerce, and industry), and public enlightenment (education). 1824 Nov 24 (Box 50, Folder 814, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Don Roman Lorenzo Calbo del Consejo de S. M. su Secretario Escrivano de Cámara en el Real y Supremo de la Guerra." Place: Madrid. Description: Mexican copies of documents the Spanish government provided to the United States government to help American citizens adjust their claims against Spain. Most texts deal with the 1797 seizure of a ship named Elysa. 1824 (Box 50, Folder 815, Reel 12)
  - Title: Codicil. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of the codicil to the last will and testament of Serafina Martínez de Arcos, the widow of Tomás Díaz de Varela. 1824 (Box 50, Folder 816, Reel 12)
  - Title: Documents from the London consulate. Place: London. Description: Copies of three letters. The first is a letter of introduction by Manuel Eduardo de Gorostiza in which he offers his services to the Mexican government. The other letters are communications to the Mexican foreign ministry signed by José Mariano de Michelena. 1824 (Box 50, Folder 817, Reel 12)
  - Title: Poetry. Description: Four verses dedicated to Agustín Itúrbide. 1824, n.d. (Box 50, Folder 818, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Voto particular." Place: [Nuevo León?] Description: Private opinion written by an unidentified member of the treasury or ecclesiastical affairs committee of [Nuevo León's state congress?], which considers three propositions concerning the formation of a board to oversee tithe collection. ca. 1824 (Box 50, Folder 819, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Secretaría de Relaciones Departmento del Exterior Año de 1824 Yndiferente Correspondencía entre esta secretaría y el Señor Baron Don Alejandro de Humboldt." Places: Mexico City and Paris. Description: Copies of three letters written to or by Alexander von Humboldt. [The text may be a copy of a publication of the Mexican Ministry of Foreign Relations.] The first letter is from Humboldt to Tomas Murphy. The last two letters are an exchange of correspondence between Humboldt and Lucas Alemán, the Mexican foreign minister. [1824?] (Box 50, Folder 820, Reel 12)
  - Title: Documents concerning a colegio. Place: San Luis Potosí and Mexico City. Description: Copies of documents related to the establishment of a colegio in San Luis Potosí. Documents concern the colegio's finances and movement of troops out of the barracks that was to house the colegio. 1824-1826 (Box 50, Folder 821, Reel 12)
  - Title: Texts concerning government in San Luis Potosí. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Handwritten copies of acts by the electoral commission; a broadside from the governor to the people; a text on the foundation of a colegio; and a report on Masonic lodges. 1824-1828 (Box 50, Folder 822, Reel 12)
  - Title: Diego Villaseñor papers. Places: Mexico City and Toluca. Description: Documents concerning the career of Diego Villaseñor, an official of the state of Mexico's treasury ministry. These texts trace Villaseñor's career from the first years of the Mexican republic to his retirement during the French intervention. Included are correspondence, letters of appointment, testimonies of service and merits, grants of leaves of absence, official documents, records of civic service, and a twenty year review of municipal accounts received by Villaseñor. 1824-1866 (Box 50, Folder 823, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter from the "Secretaría del Congreso del Estado Libre de Tamaulipas." Place: Ciudad Victoria. Description: Letter to the Coahuila state congress stating that Villa de Aguayo had been renamed Ciudad Victoria. 1825 Apr 25 (Box 51, Folder 824, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Proyecto de Reglamento para el Archivo general." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of the regulations governing the Archivo General de la Nación. Also included is a copy of the cover letter from the archive's director to the minister of interior. [1825 May 6?] (Box 51, Folder 825, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter from the "Secretaría del Congreso del Estado de Tabasco." Place: Villahermosa. Description: Letter addressed to Coahuila's state congress stating Tabasco's constituent congress had adjourned. 1825 May 20 (Box 51, Folder 826, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter from the Mexican consul in New York. Place: New York. Description: Translation of a letter by the Mexican consul in New York, originally written on 1825 June 11, concerning the entry requirements for passengers and ships traveling between the United States and Mexico. The letter also discusses entry requirements for ships' cargos. 1825 Sep 8 (Box 51, Folder 827, Reel 12)
  - Title: Petition. Place: Mexico City. Description: Petition by José Ignacio Yáñes seeking appointment as cavalry colonel with the requisite pension in recognition of his services. Yáñes describes his military service in the early part of the independence revolt under Hidalgo and Matamoros, as well as his rejoining the movement under Itúrbide. 1825 Jun 15 (Box 51, Folder 828, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter from the Ministerio de Justicia. Place: Mexico. Description: Letter to the governor of Coahuila signed by Miguel [Ramos?] Arispe concerning prisoners. 1825 Aug 3 (Box 51, Folder 829, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Departamento de Cuentas Razón del Ministerio de Hacienda." Place: Mexico City. Description: Certificate reviewing the employment history and conduct of Diego Villaseñor Cervantes. 1825 Sep 20 (Box 51, Folder 830, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter from the "Secretaría del Congreso del Estado Libre de Durango." Place: Durango. Description: Cover letter for two copies of the Durango state constitution sent to Coahuila's state congress. 1825 Oct 14 (Box 51, Folder 831, Reel 12)
  - Title: Dispatch from the "Secretaría de Guerra y Marina." Place: Mexico City. Description: Dispatch concerning military aid the federal government provided Coahuila in response to Comanche Indian attacks. The text also mentions slights against the federal government by Coahuila's state government. 1825 Oct 19 (Box 51, Folder 832, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter to the ayuntamiento. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Unsigned letter concerning the need to collect interest payments on loans which had been designated for the financial support of three "escuelas gratuitas de niños." 1825 Nov 18 (Box 51, Folder 833, Reel 12)
  - Title: Letter from the "Secretaría del Congreso de Coahuila y Tejas." Place: Saltillo. Description: Letter to the governor concerning Indian attacks on the frontier and measures to deal with the raids. 1825 Nov 28 (Box 51, Folder 834, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Amado Padre." Description: Letter written by José María to his beloved father denouncing his father's political stand with "Aza" against Joaquín [José Joaquín Fernández de Lizardi?]. 1825 Dec 11 (Box 51, Folder 835, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Listas nominadas de la fuerza presente en el día que se rindió el castillo de Ulúa acredora por esto al doble haver concedido por S.E. el Presidente de la Nación." Place: Veracruz. Description: Lists of soldiers who served in the different companies of the second permanent battalion on the day the Spanish garrison surrendered the San Juan de Ulúa fort to Mexican forces. A handdrawn plan of the fort is also included. 1825 (Box 51, Folder 836, Reel 12)
  - Title: Inventory and rental. Places: Mexico City and Puebla. Description: Inventory of a bakery and its dependencies located on San Juan de Dios Street in Puebla. Also included is a copy of the rental contract for the bakery and its dependencies between José Leonardo Torija, the attorney for Serfia Martínez de Arcos, and Cayetano Ramiro. 1825 (Box 51, Folder 837, Reel 12)
  - Title: "Esamen de los curatos de México...." Place: [Mexico City?]. Description: Religious text which discusses seven questions: what type of priests were most suitable for the conversion of gentiles; what types of priest were best suited to preserve the religious practices of those who had been converted; what types of ministers had undertaken conversions in New Spain; and questions concerning the size of dioceses. 1825 (Box 51, Folder 838, Reel 13)
  - Title: Correspondence concerning a colegio. Places: San Miguel [Mesqe?], San Luis Potosí, and Salinas de Peñon Blanca. Description: Four letters dealing with the establishment of a colegio in San Luis Potosí. The first letter concerns Governor José Ildefonso Díaz de León's donation of three hundred pesos to the colegio. The remaining three letters deal with Juan González's mission to obtain donations for the colegio. 1825-1826 (Box 51, Folder 839, Reel 13)
  - Title: Documents concerning Lucas Alamán. Place: Mexico City. Description: Correspondence written by Lucas Alamán consisting of a letter to the governor of Coahuila concerning a papal encyclical; two letters addressed to the governor of San Luis Potosí concerning a brief revolt by that state's militia; and a copy of a letter addressed to José Mariano Michelena. 1825-1830 (Box 51, Folder 840, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Plan que manifiesta el número de habitantes...." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Population of the state of San Luis Potosí listed by district, village, age, and sex. ca. 1825
    See: Oversize, folder 12
  - Title: Appointment. Place: Mexico City. Description: Appointment of Manuel Eduardo de Gorostiza as Mexican chargé d'affaires in the Low Countries. 1826 Feb 12 (Box 51, Folder 841, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Primera Secretaría de Estado - Sección de Gobierno." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a list of documents transferred to the national archive by government order, and an unsigned letter concerning the need to transfer certain documents to the national archive. 1826 Apr 4-21 (Box 51, Folder 842, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Ystrucciones que se ha dirijido a las comisarías para qe. se observen en todas las Aduanas Marítimas qe están a su cargo." Place: Mexico City. Description: Series of instructions detailing the required procedures to permit the entry of a ship's cargo into Mexico. The responsibilities of various port and treasury officials are also detailed. 1826 May 26 (Box 51, Folder 843, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Sor. Juez de Solitas." Place: [Mexico City?]. Description: Solicitation by a parish priest to the judge of "solitas" seeking the needed dispensations to legitimize the children of José Rafael Ocaña and Joaquina Bruna. Bruna was Ocaña's niece and goddaughter. Ocaña and Bruna had been living together as if they were married for many years. 1826 May 29 (Box 51, Folder 844, Reel 13)
  - Title: "D. Pedro Montesdeoca por María Francisca Brito...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Communciation [to the court?] by María Francisca Brito's legal representative in a legal case with Mariano Pérez de Castro. A note signed Ruiz de Castañeda appears on the back. 1826 Oct 2 (Box 51, Folder 845, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Ynforme en que se demuestra la importancia de los Archivos - su origen y antiguedad en México y organización del presente." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a report by the director of the national archive discussing the organization's importance, history, and administrative structure. 1826 Oct 13 (Box 51, Folder 846, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Ynventario de la madera, herramienta, y demás perteneciente a la obra del Palacio Consistorial...." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Inventory of wood, tools, and other things being used in the construction of San Luis Potosí's town hall. 1826 (Box 51, Folder 847, Reel 13)
  - Title: Documents concerning Pedro García de Arista. Places: Mexico City. Description: Included are several notarized personal testimonies of aid García de Arista provided to the independence movement while he was a member of the Spanish army; texts concerning contributions for the celebration of independence day; and a letter from Pedro José Muñoz. 1826-1829 (Box 51, Folder 848, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Presupuesto de la Tesorería General...." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Budget calculations for 1827 listing the projected income and expenditures of the state of San Luis Potosí. 1827 Jan 3
    See: Oversize, folder 13
  - Title: Final sentence. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Ruling sentencing Manuel [Montañes?] to six months of community service for shouting "Viva España." 1827 Feb 7 (Box 51, Folder 849, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Lista de los Europeos que se hallan en este suelo de San Luis Potosí...." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: List of Europeans, mainly Spaniards, who had presented themselves to an unidentified court. Information about each individual's marital status, place of origin, age, profession, and legal status in Mexico is included. 1827 Feb 16 (Box 51, Folder 850, Reel 13)
  - Title: Final sentence. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Ruling sentencing Esteban Farfán to three years service in the Veracruz presidio for shouting "Viva España." The same ruling acquitted Perfecto Cubillos of all charges. 1827 Feb 20 (Box 51, Folder 851, Reel 13)
  - Title: Communication to the honorable congress. Description: Brief note from an unidentified person stating that the press/printing regulation was in his possession. The letter also discusses the payment of salaries by the police committee. 1827 Mar 29 (Box 51, Folder 852, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Noticias pa. el Exmo. Sor. Governador tocante a la estinguida diputación de minería." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Document detailing the history of land owned by the [San Luis Potosí?] mining deputation in Monte de Caldera. 1827 Apr 19 (Box 51, Folder 853, Reel 13)
  - Author: Eguía, Jose Ignacio. Title: "Noticias que el Exmo. Señor Gobernador, tocando a la extinguida diputación de minería." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Handwritten notes on a text concerning the history of certain mines and actions of the San Luis Potosí mining deputation. Also included is an index summarizing three documents concerning the San Luis Potosí mining deputation. 1827 Apr 19 (Box 51, Folder 854, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Exmo. Sor en oficio de veinte y ocho del próximo pasado dice a este ayuntamiento...." Description: Document concerning the public granary (pósito) of an unidentified city. The text lays out the regulations of the pósito. Relevant legal points concerning the administration and control of the pósito's funds are also discussed. 1827 Jun 8 (Box 51, Folder 855, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Conducta qe. adopta la mayoría de la guarnición de esta plaza para sostener los Altos Poderes de la Federación...." Place: Veracruz. Description: Five rules of conduct adopted by men serving in the Veracruz garrison. 1827 Jul 31 (Box 51, Folder 856, Reel 13)
  - Title: "Observaciones q. el Departamto. de Cuenta y razón de la Secretaría de Hacienda hace sobre el dictamen de la comisión 1a. de este ramo de la cámara de representantes del Congreso gral. para el arreglo de Aranceles de Aduanas marítimas, agregando los indicaciones de las faltas q. cree notar en él." Place: Mexico City. Description: Two copies of detailed observations made by a department of the national treasury about each article of the maritime customs duty schedule. The author describes the intent of each article and any perceived fault. Also included are the same department's observations about the maritime customs schedule's classification and nomenclature; points that the tariff regulations lacked; and proposals for the regulation of ships involved in the internal coastal trade. 1827 Sep 4 (Box 51, Folder 857, Reel 13)
  - Title: Draft of "observaciones." Place: Mexico City. Description: Preliminary draft or outline of the detailed observations made by a department of the national treasury about the articles of the maritime customs duty schedule. [1827 Sep 4?] (Box 51, Folder 858, Reel 13)
  - Title: Letter to Juan Leonido Reinoso. Place: Tenería. Description: Request by José Salvador Muñoz for Reinoso to draw up a new legal document concerning a slave. 1827 Sep 20 (Box 51, Folder 859, Reel 13)
  - Title: Documents concerning the expulsion of the Spanish. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Acknowledgment of the receipt of the decree expelling the Spanish from Mexico and a communication from the state's comisaría general to the governor discussing particular points of the law of expulsion. 1827 Dec 31 (Box 51, Folder 860, Reel 13)
  - Title: Documents concerning slaves. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Documents concerning the emancipation of three slaves belonging to Melchor Sánchez Navarro and Polonia Veray. 1827 (Box 51, Folder 861, Reel 13)
  - Title: Documents concerning a seizure. Place: Puebla. Description: [Incomplete?] set of documents concerning a seizure of French gingham in Puebla. 1827 (Box 51, Folder 862, Reel 13)
  - Title: Documents concerning the Colegio Guadalupano Josefino. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Documents mainly concerning the resignation of a professor and the effort to replace him. 1827 (Box 51, Folder 863, Reel 13)
  - Title: Texts concerning government in San Luis Potosí. Place: San Luis Potosí and Huehuetlan. Description: Included are a letter addressed to the governor concerning a very old man; a communication to the governor from Huehuetlan's ayuntamiento about the emancipation of slaves; and a chart showing the state's administrative divisions. 1827 (Box 51, Folder 864, Reel 13)
  - Title: Cristóbal Gil de Castro-José María de Aguilar correspondence. Places: Mexico City and Orizaba. Description: Five letters in which the correspondents discuss the financial situation of the marchioness of Colina, and other matters. 1827 (Box 51, Folder 865, Reel 13)